<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Publications on Yan Tang</title><link>https://ehehe.cn/publications/</link><description>Recent content in Publications on Yan Tang</description><generator>Hugo -- 0.154.5</generator><language>zh-cn</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ehehe.cn/publications/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Flow-SAR: Cross-Domain SAR Image Translation Using Flow Models</title><link>https://ehehe.cn/publications/2025-flow-sar/</link><pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ehehe.cn/publications/2025-flow-sar/</guid><description>We propose Flow-SAR, a two-stage SAR image cross-domain translation framework using invertible flow models to address domain discrepancy in SAR target recognition. Unlike GAN-based methods that suffer from training instability, Flow-SAR maps domains to a shared latent space with Gaussian prior and aligns distributions through latent translation. The framework first estimates a global translation vector for coarse alignment, then refines with class-specific vectors using pseudo-labeling to enhance intra-class consistency. Experiments on SAMPLE dataset show Flow-SAR improves both visual realism and target recognition performance.</description></item><item><title>Through-Wall Human Activity Recognition with Compact MIMO Ultra-Wideband Radar</title><link>https://ehehe.cn/publications/2025-through-wall-har/</link><pubDate>Mon, 14 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ehehe.cn/publications/2025-through-wall-har/</guid><description>An integrated human activity recognition system that combines compact MIMO ultra-wideband radar with deep learning approaches, achieving 99% recognition accuracy in through-wall environments and representing an 8% improvement over state-of-the-art methods.</description></item><item><title>Ultra-Lightweight Automatic License Plate Recognition System for Microcontrollers: A Cost-Effective and Energy-Efficient Solution</title><link>https://ehehe.cn/publications/2024-tiny-alpr/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ehehe.cn/publications/2024-tiny-alpr/</guid><description>A novel ultra-lightweight ALPR system specifically designed for deployment on microcontrollers, offering a cost-effective and energy-efficient solution for large-scale applications and naturally mitigates the issues of large perspective transformations frequently encountered in real-world settings.</description></item><item><title>Style Reconstruction-Driven Networks for Occlusion-Aware License Plate Recognition</title><link>https://ehehe.cn/publications/2024-style-reconstruction/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ehehe.cn/publications/2024-style-reconstruction/</guid><description>A novel style reconstruction-based network that can transform input license plates into standardized images and addresses the class imbalance in existing license plate datasets by computes character prediction confidence using a lightweight matching module.</description></item><item><title>A CFAR-Enhanced Ship Detector for SAR Images Based on YOLOv5s</title><link>https://ehehe.cn/publications/2024-cfar-ship-detector/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ehehe.cn/publications/2024-cfar-ship-detector/</guid><description>Proposes a YOLOv5s-based ship detection method for SAR images with CFAR enhancement. The method introduces a sub-net to learn traditional features, augmenting ship feature representation and incorporating frequency-domain information into channel attention mechanisms, achieving 68.04% detection accuracy and 60.25% recall with a compact 18.51M model size.</description></item><item><title>结合行驶场景语义的轨迹-路网实时匹配方法</title><link>https://ehehe.cn/publications/2021-realtime-map-matching/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ehehe.cn/publications/2021-realtime-map-matching/</guid><description>提出了一种结合行驶场景语义的轨迹-路网实时匹配方法。该方法在智能交通、自动驾驶等领域起着关键作用，通过考虑行驶场景的语义信息来提高地图匹配的准确性和实时性。</description></item></channel></rss>